# Peter John Rooke

Whickham, Gateshead, Tyne and Wear.

Mobile: 07540 635 058

Email: peter.rooke.work@gmail.com

## **Overview**

Software development consultant specialising in Java and Spring based technologies.

# **Technologies**

Java / JEE	Java 8, JSP, JSF, Java Messaging Service (JMS), Web Services (SOAP / REST).	
Spring 4	Spring MVC, Spring REST, Spring Data, Spring JPA, Spring JDBC, Spring AOP, Spring Intergration, Spring Batch, Spring Boot, Spring Concurrency.	
Other Languages	JavaScript, Sybase Transact SQL (TSQL), Informix 4GL / SQL, Powerbuilder, Shell Scripts, XML, XSLT, HTML, UML.	
Middleware	Oracle Weblogic Fusion Middleware (SOA BPM), Oracle Service Bus, Oracle OHS, Apache Tomcat, Sun Application Server.	
Security Clearance	Held clearances for various projects since 2010.	

# **Professional Certifications**

Pivotal Spring Professional – Spring 4	August 2015
Sun Certified Associate for the Java 2 Platform 1.5	July 2005
Sun Certified Programmer for the Java 2 Platform 1.4	August 2005
CISCO CCNA1 Networking Fundamentals	January 2005

## **Academic Qualifications**

B.Sc.Computing - University Of Northumbria. 1996 – 2000

BTEC ONC Computer Studies - South Tyneside College. 1991 (Day release).

5 GCE O Levels – Heworth Grange Comprehensive. 1987.

## **Computer Training / Courses**

Pivotal Enterprise Spring – October 2015.

Pivotal Core Spring – September 2014.

Credit Derivatives, Equity Derivatives. April 2007 / May 2008

Sybase SQL (II, III), XML – April 2007 / May 2008.

# **Employment History**

<u>Self Study</u> - Java / Spring certification [May 2015 – Present]

Technologies: Java, Spring, Amazon Web Services, TOGAF.

For the past year, I've taken time off from the contract market. My aim is to enhance my skills and knowledge, and gain some valuable certifications. I've completed the Spring 4 Professional certification last year, and I am currently working towards the various Amazon Web Services certifications, with an initial focus on the solutions architect. In addition I have started my work towards the TOGAF architecture framework certification.

As a Spring Core Professional I'm competent in the areas of; dependency injection, the spring bean life cycle, unit testing and mocking, aspect orientated programming (AOP), database integration using JPA (Hibernate) and Spring Data, web development using spring MVC, web services with REST and SOAP, Transactions, Java messaging services (JMS), Security, Remote method invocation (RMI) and the Java management extensions (JMX). For the Spring enterprise integration course the following topics were covered; enterprise integration approaches, enterprise integration patterns (EIP), concurrency, SOA web services using REST and SOAP, Java messaging services (JMS), Spring Integration, Spring Batch, global and local transactions, and lastly remote method invocation (RMI).

#### Mastek UK Ltd - Java Developer [September 2014 – April 2015]

Technologies: Java, Sun Application Server, Solaris Unix, Maven, Jenkins, Subversion, Scrum Working on a Heath and Social Care Information Centre (now NHS Digital) system we successfully transitioned the SUS patient records system which has previous been hosted by an external supplier.

Java development using a custom JSP based framework. Maintenance of the existing system which uploaded and transformed patient record information into a large data warehouse. A part of my role was to build the live environments middleware components. In the final stages of the project I built the new live production system and completed the final application deployment during the transfer of service in late February.

British Airways (via Leighton Systems) - Software Engineer [January 2014 – June 2014] Technologies: Java, JMS, Web Services, SOAP UI, Weblogic, Tomcat, Oracle, Linux, Scrum, Kanban While at BA I worked on the airlines Orders Data Store, which was the airlines internal booking information system. The system existed to reduce the costs of interacting with the central booking system Amadeus. We used custom third party software supplied by SABRE which processed information in real time using a customised domain specific language. Our information was available to other internal BA systems as we developed and provided SOAP based web services.

The role included Scrum based Java development (later we changed to Kanban). writing customised software in the proprietary DSL, developing and maintaining SOAP web services, as well as regression testing using Soap UI. I was also responsible for the building of some new environments using WebLogic and Tomcat middleware.

Atos - WebLogic Middleware Specialist [November 2011 – November 2013] Technologies: Oracle WebLogic, Fusion Middleware, Oracle OHS, Java, JMS, SOA BPM, ANT, WLST For the Home Office immigration case worker (ICW) account I was responsible for the deployment and maintenance of a large UKBA system. My role was to build middleware environments and then deploy and configure each new weekly release. In the final stages of the project I successful deployed

The software was based on the latest WebLogic fusion middleware from Oracle, so SOA BPM, OSB

the first production release and upgrades on the live system.

with an additional Informatica MDM solution. We operated in an agile environment, with very short delivery timetables.

In addition, for another NHS project, I built an Oracle HTTP server (Apache httpd) environment. These servers were used to provide load balancing and reverse proxies to a WebLogic OBIEE application.

<u>Fujitsu</u> – Java Developer / Configuration Management [January 2011 – October 2011] Technologies: Java, Spring, JPA, Hibernate, JSF, CFX, Weblogic, Tomcat, T-SQL, MS-SQL Server, Maven, ANT, Bamboo, VMware. Jira, Agile development.

As part of the UKBA's immigration project, I worked on the Points Based System (PBS) as a Java developer / build manager. The project used the Fujitsu APT development method and we preformed test driven development using Agile practices. I helped to implement use cases using Java / Spring JSF / JPA / Hibernate / Transact SQL. We used Spring CFX based web services to exchange information between the various application tiers.

I was also responsible for weekly building, deploying and then packaging of the software artefacts. These were then handed over to a third party hosting company. After a successful live release the software development for the project was given to the hosting company Atos.

Strategic Software Solutions / Citigroup – Developer [July 2010 - January 2011] Technologies: Sybase, T-SQL, Java, C, Lex, Yacc, Unix, Shell Scripts, SWIFT messages. For Citigroup my major project was to enhance the DOGS settlement system so that it was able to process new SWIFT message formats. I modified Lex and Yacc based parsers so they could process new message tags to comply with the new 2010 standard. From a detailed specification document I enhanced the parser code, performed unit and then regression testing. Finally it was prepared for release into the live environment.

British Telecom – Applications Support / Development [June 2008 – March 2010] Technologies: Java, J2EE, Weblogic, XML, Struts, Oracle PL/SQL, UNIX, EIstream Workflow. I supported a legacy system called Disclosure Scotland that performed criminal record checks on applications. Using Java, shell scripts and Oracle PL/SQL I implemented many utility programs that were used to maintain the system. My knowledge of Java technologies and WebLogic was used in order to understand the more complex functional problems within the system. I was involved with the implementation of a disaster recovery solution alongside providing daily support using a wide range of technologies. We also provide out of hours coverage to ensure that the system is available at all times.

JP Morgan – Applications Developer [March 2007 – May 2008] Technologies: Sybase Stored Procedures, Java, XSLT, JMS, IBM MQ, UNIX, Equity and Credit Derivatives.

I worked within the Pyramid Trade Processing feeds team within the Exotics and Hybrids back office team. My responsibility was to provide trade information to other downstream back office systems. These typically involved gaining an understanding of customer requirements, creating a T-SQL stored procedure to extract the information and then implementing this using a custom Java feed database extraction system. I added some additional enhancements to extend the functionality of this tool.

My major projects were; a fast expiry tool for options, addition of a new legal entity to enable new regions to feed foreign exchange futures to other downstream systems for both payments and reconciliation.

OSG Ship Management Ltd – Applications Developer [February 2006 – March 2007] Technologies: Java, JEE, Java Server Pages, Servlets, Struts, JDBC, EJB2, Oracle PL/SQL, UML, iPlanet, BEA Weblogic, OC4J.

At OSG I delivered two small web based systems. Initially working from the New York office, I visited the HR and Shipping departments to gather user requirements. Then from the Newcastle office I designed and developed their systems using agile methods. We were using custom servlet framework (similar to structs) which used the major J2EE technologies and design patterns.

The companies HR department were implementing a bonus system, and I developed a web based system using use cases, prototyping, Java server pages, JavaScript, JDBC, and PL/SQL.

My second project was a technology migration rewrite for an old shipping market analysis application. To do this I re-engineered an old Sybase Powerbuilder / Infomaker /Adaptive Server Anywhere system. The new system was redeveloped as a J2EE / Oracle application.

North Tyneside Council – Applications Development Officer [March 2005 – February 2006] Technologies: Informix SQL, MS Access / SQL Server, VB6, Shell Scripts, XML, Mobile Devices (iPAQ's), UNIX.

Support and development for applications in the property, fleet transport, CCTV security, and crime related business areas. Development of a system to help the management of CCTV cameras and record incidents. Installation of an I2 system to help crime prevention.

#### **BBC Technology - Applications Developer** [August 2001 – May 2004]

Technologies: Java / J2EE; JSP, Servlets, JAXP, XML, Informix 4GL / SQL, UML, UNIX, Shell Scripts, Expect Scripts.

Development, support and maintenance on the <u>Infax</u> system which was an information repository and media library of broadcasted programmes.

Some of my projects were; development of a Java module to load XML data from an external system, improving a data feed that took information from news items, development of a suit of shell / expect / 4GL scripts which allowed the automatic addition of new users, I also performed various maintenance programming tasks in the form of bug fixes.

**Spark Response** (formally Mailcom) – **Programmer** [August 2000 – August 2001]

Technologies: Informix 4GL / SQL, MS Access, Shell Scripts, Linux and UNIX.

Development of software for inbound and outbound call centre business operations. I developed a solution for the warranty registration of Fiat / Alfa Romeo motor cars, and help with the maintenance of existing systems for our clients including: B&Q, British Airways, Huggies.

<u>Datawright Computer Services</u> – Powerbuilder Developer [July 1999 – August 2000]

Technologies: Powerbuilder, Sybase Adaptive Server, Mapinfo GIS.

Working in a small team, I developed a system using Powerbuilder. The software was used by local governments in their planning and building control departments. .

<u>University Of Northumbria</u> – Full time student [September 1996 – July 1999]

Technologies: Java, C++, Prolog, Oracle SQL, UML, OMT, BOOCH, Yourdon, SSADM.

Computing degree featuring business analysis, software design, programming and database theory.

<u>Territorial Army</u> - Royal Engineers Lance Corporal [1995 – 2000 (part time)].

Participated in a medium girder bridge (MGB) speed build completion, taught combat engineering at various cadet camps, and normal duties. I ran both the clothing and G10 tools store together with supervising and carrying out combat engineer tasks. Achieved B2 combat engineering skills and was based in Newcastle with 103 Field Squadron, 72 Engineer Regiment.

Regular Army (Royal Logistic Corps) – Private. [July 1994 – September 1994].

Mailcom. – 4GL Programmer [February 1994 – June 1994]

Technologies: Informix 4GL / SQL, Shell Scripts, UNIX,

Development and support of Informix 4GL database software for this mail order company.

#### Bowater Liquid Packaging Limited – 4GL Programmer [1992 – 1994]

Technologies: Informix 4GL/SQL, C, Shell Scripts. UNIX

Development and software support in a manufacturing business. Using a bought in package, I implemented a both stock control system which utilised cyclic counting and a purchasing module. I also helped to implement a new material requirements planning (MRP) solution.

<u>Whessoe Computer Systems</u> (Formally QRS Computing) – C Programmer [1990 – 1992] Technologies: C, Shell Scripts, UNIX

Working in this software house I helped develop maintenance management or planed preventative maintenance systems. I customised the core product to produce solutions for large shipyards.

## MARI Advanced Training Limited - Computer Trainee [1987 - 1990]

Technologies: Shell Scripts, Pascal, C, FoxPro / Clipper, Turbo Basic, Speech Technology (text to speech and voice recognition)

As computer trainees, we received a good grounding in programming and software development. I also was taught basic electronics. After spending six months on placement with a company called Aptech, developing solutions using speech technologies, I gained employment with the company.

### **Personal Details**

Date of Birth: May 1971.

Marital Status: Single, no children.

Driving Licences: Car and Motorbike (clean).

Gender: Male.

Nationality: British (since birth).

#### Other Awards

<u>B2 Combat Engineer / Military:</u> Military engineering: water supply, mine warfare, demolitions, medium girder bridge, heavy / medium girder over bridge, bulk fuel handling, Harrier air support, basic military engineering skills, all arms stores and accountancy, first aid, nuclear biological and chemical training, map reading, field craft, skill at arms, basic instruction techniques, junior leadership.

RSSL Public Lifeguard – aquatic rescue and first aid qualification for indoor swimming pools.

<u>PADI Diving</u> – Open water and advanced open water diver, together with the enriched air certification.

# **Hobbies and Sports**

As a keen sportsman I regularly swim, cycle, and weight train. My hobbies include photography, old cars, motorbikes and traditional martial arts (budo taijutsu / ninjutsu).

#### **Social Media**

Linked In (public profile): <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/peter-rooke-public/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/peter-rooke-public/</a>

Linked In (private profile): <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/peterrooke/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/peterrooke/</a> (colleagues only)